Guide to the Americans For Immigrant Justice Records, 1982-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Americans For Immigrant Justice records 1982-2011
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Americans for Immigrant Justice
31.5 Linear Feet 23625 Items
Americans for Immigrant Justice (formerly Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center [FIAC]) is a not-for-profit legal assistance organization dedicated to protecting and promoting the basic human rights of immigrants of all nationalities. The Americans for Immigrant Justice records span the years of 1980-2011. The collection contains project files and correspondence regarding immigrant detention policy and conditions in the state of Florida, particularly concerning the Haitian community; legal documents regarding the same, including restricted and confidential legal files; and audiovisual material produced by or for FIAC. The bulk of materials are organized by subject and detention facility.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The Legal Files Series is restricted. Researchers must receive prior authorization from AI Justice in order to access the material in this series. All other series are unrestricted. Once authorization has been granted, AI Justice will contact the Rubenstein Library directly and provide name of researcher, dates of use, and which boxes may be accessed..
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Americans For Immigrant Justice Records were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in.
Historical Note
Americans for Immigrant Justice (formerly Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC)) is a not-for-profit legal assistance organization dedicated to protecting and promoting the basic human rights of immigrants of all nationalities.
Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC) was founded in 1996 because of pending restrictions and funding cuts to Legal Services Corporation (LSC) funded agencies, which prevented many organizations in the state of Florida from serving the immigrant population. Sweeping changes in immigration law and welfare reform also increased the demand for services from FIAC. In 2011 After 15 years of helping immigrants obtain legal status, successfully litigating their unjust treatment and pressing for constructive immigration laws and policy, the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC) became Americans for Immigrant Justice (AI Justice for short and Americanos Pro Justicia Inmigrante in Spanish)to better reflect the national focus and depth of their work. firm.
Collection Overview
The Americans for Immigrant Justice (AIJ) records, formerly the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center (FIAC), span the years of 1980-2011. This collection contains extensive documentation of the events and crises surrounding asylum, deportation, detention and abuses that took place within Florida detention centers from the years 1980 to 2011, as well as documentation regarding issues of repatriation. It records the efforts of FIAC to advocate on behalf of immigrant and refugee populations in Florida during this time. The majority of material in this collection deals with Haitians seeking asylum in the U.S., but also includes material on Cuban refugees. Many files focus on Cheryl Little's work with child refugees and detainees and their asylum claims, and on discrimination against female immigrants. Files also include material on interdiction at sea and related court documents, government immigration policy pre- and post-9/11, documentation on hunger strikes at various facilities, material related to the Haitian Boat crises, and documentation of raids on immigrant populations. The detention facilities of particular concern in this collection include Guantanamo, Krome, and Turner Guilford Knight correctional facilities, as well as Florida's county jails.
The collection contains legal documents related to the activity of FIAC, including affidavits of detainees held in Florida facilities, and other court documents, such as court pleadings and briefings; reports on facility conditions; correspondence, including correspondence between detainees and their families, letters from concerned citizens, and formal correspondence between FIAC, especially Cheryl Little, and other organizations and officials; case studies and reports on immigration and refugee crises, and reports of abuses and conditions in Florida detention facilities; FBI interviews with detainees; related articles and speeches; restricted material, including medical records; and promotional and educational videos produced by or for FIAC, documentary footage of missions and events, and press conference and news footage.
The series in this collection include the Detention Series, the Immigrant and Refugees Series, the Legal Files Series, the General Organizational Records Series, the Audiovisual Series and the Photographic Materials Series. The bulk of the material for this collection belongs to the Detention Series and the Immigrant and Refugees Series.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
Guantánamo Bay Detention Camp
Krome Detention Center
Little, Cheryl
Asylum, Right of
Detention of persons -- Government policy -- United States
Hunger strikes -- Detention of persons -- United States
Immigrants -- United States
Maritime law -- Immigrants -- United States
Prisons -- Florida
Refugees -- Civil rights
Refugees -- Haitians
Refugees -- Cubans
Repatriation -- Haitians
Return migration -- Haiti
Unaccompanied refugee children -- United States
Women immigrants-Abuse of -- Alien detention centers -- United States
Women immigrants -- Discrimination -- United States
Black and white photographs
Color photographs
Legal documents -- Refugees -- United States
Videocassettes
Florida -- Immigration advocates
United States -- Alien detention centers
Contents of Collection
- Detention Series, 1982-2002, (16 boxes)
  Series contains documents related to detention facilities holding immigrant and refugee populations of interest to Florida Immigration Advocacy Center, particularly Haitian populations. The series focuses on Krome, Turner Guilford Knight, and Guantanamo detention facilities as well as county jails and other facilities holding immigrants and refugees. Many files deal with allegations of abuse and mismanagement within the facilities. Files include legal documents such as affidavits and court records and other materials such as newspaper articles, correspondence, government reports, and PR materials. Also included are files related to Haitian asylum and repatriation and materials related to Guantanamo children and child refugees. Sensitive and confidential material has been moved to the Legal Files series. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  - Guantanamo Subseries, 1992-1997
    Subseries contains materials related to Guantanamo detention facility, particularly with regard to the Haitian population and child refugees detained at Guantanamo. The subseries includes affidavits, emergency action and funding requests, reports on facility conditions, correspondence, press releases and published reports.
    - Action/Support for Guantanamo minors (Box 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee
    - Guantanamo Affidavits (clean copy) trip: 1994 Dec. 6-10
    - Guantanamo Affidavits (clean copy) trip: 1995 Jan. 18-20
    - Articles, 1994-1995
    - Assisting refugees at Guantanamo, 1994-1995
    - Guantanamo Children Informational Packet, 1995 April 25
    - Donna Abbott - Guantanamo reports
    - Double backers and returnees new article
    - Emergency funding to assist Guantanamo detainees settling in Florida
    - Guantanamo, 1991-1992
    - Guantanamo Children - emergency action requests
      Amnesty and Tap Tap meeting.
    - Guantanamo Children - flights to Guantanamo
      Air Sunshine.
    - Guantanamo Children - rally protesting detention, 1995 Jan. 7
    - Guantanamo Children - team background information
      When in Haiti.
    - Fate returnees
    - Guantanamo - forms
    - General - Gray, William
    - General - Guantanamo reports
      Background, etc.
    - General information
    - Guantanamo's H's-M's - Reparole and EAD, 1996 (Box 2)
    - Haitian asylum: Coven
      Beyer memo.
    - Haitian asylum/country conditions, 1996
    - Haitians denied citizenship
    - Haitian Guantanamo cases/A.O., 1997
    - Haiti report, 1995
      Karla Pearcy, 1995 Aug. 8.
    - Haiti trip - repatriated Haitians
    - Interview/returnees, 1992 Feb.
      Originals, etc.
    - Letters: Congressional etc., 1994 Nov. - 1995 July
    - Letters - Reno, 1995
      U.S. Attorney General.
    - Letters - Waxman packet, 1995 July
    - Meissner's open letter to Haitian community, 1994 August 5
    - Memos, reports, and letters on regulations and policy in Guantanamo
    - Mildred Aristide packet
    - Not in Their Best Interest: A Report on the U.S. Government's Forcible Repatriation of Guantanamo's Unaccompanied Haitian Children, 1995 May (Box 3)
    - Guantanamo packet, 1995 Feb., (3 folders)
    - Guantanamo packet - update, 1995 Mar. 22
    - P. Coven meeting 1996, Aug. 2
    - Petitions/Letters of support
    - Post-Guantanamo
    - Press conferences, 1995
      Guantanamo Children, Jan. 24, March 8, March 31, May 22, June 29, July 31.
    - Press: general file
    - Press Releases, 1994 Dec. 12 and 1996 April 1
    - Guantanamo processing, 1992
    - Resolutions
    - Special immigrant status for foster children
    - Supplemental information, 1994-1996, Guantanamo, (3 folders)
    - UNHCR correspondence
    - Update reports
  - Krome Subseries, 1982-2000
    Subseries contains materials related to Krome detention facility, including some material on children's asylum claims. The subseries includes affidavits, articles, correspondence, reports about facility conditions and policies, information on the hunger strike, and court cases files.
    - 79th St. Incident, 1990 July (Box 4)
    - Abuse/ILEMP/Krome, 1990
    - Abuses, 1989, 1991, 1993
    - Abuses at Krome, 1989, (2 folders)
    - Access to Krome, 1998
    - Krome Affidavits, 2000
    - Affidavits of Abuse, 1989-1991
    - Affidavits and Articles, pp.1-220, (10 folders)
    - Affidavit: Medcraft (Box 5)
    - Affidavits - no names, incl. rape
    - Transfer Affs and others, 1991 April 4
    - Airport Ct. 1996-1997
    - Akburak, Nazim
    - Amnesty International 1989-1993
    - Articles and letters, 1986-1992
    - Articles/reports/letters 1991-1994
      Re: Haiti issues.
    - Article, Haiti: An Island Between Seasons, Shacocks, Bob. Harper's Bazaar, 1987 Feb.
    - Articles re: Krome, 1990-1996
    - Article, Spirit-Murdering the Messenger, Williams, Patricia.
    - Krome, Attorney Access, 1985
    - Krome Background, 1996
    - Chiles v. Moore, (4 folders)
    - Concerns at Krome, 1998 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, Krome, 1998
    - Correspondence, Krome, 1999
    - Correspondence, 1999-2000
    - Correspondence, 2002
    - Detention Forum, 1996 Feb. 16
    - Double standard, 1986-1990
    - Tony Ebibillio Epken
    - Ebibillo Tony
    - Fat Pack II
    - FOIA - investigation on Krome, 1998
    - FTCA, 1991
    - Haitian Arrivals, 1998 May 16
    - HRC v. Reno, (3 folders) (Box 7)
    - Hunger strike, 1991
    - Hunger strike, 1992-1993
    - Informational, inside Krome, policies and more, 1998
    - INS detention standards
    - INS detention standards, 1998
    - INS guidelines for children's asylum claims, 1998
    - Kattola v. Reno, (3 of 6 folders)
    - Kattola v. Reno, (3 of 6 folders) (Box 8)
    - Krome 1982
    - Krome 1986
    - Krome 1987
    - Krome 1988
    - Krome 1989, (4 folders)
    - Krome 1990 (Box 9)
    - Krome, 1990 April 12
      Haitian complaints against Krome detention center.
    - Krome, 1990-1991
    - Krome, 1992
    - Krome, 1996
      Includes Krome tour, 1996 April.
    - Krome, 1999, (3 folders)
    - Krome's Invisible Prisoners: Cycles of Abuse and Neglect, 1996 July
    - Krome reports
    - Krome Organization Intervention Report, 1997
    - Krome Report, 1991, (1 of 5)
    - Krome Report, 1991, (2-5 of 5) (Box 10)
    - Krome Report, final originals, 1991 June
    - Krome update urgent action letters
    - Letters from HRC attorneys to INS officials and others, Krome
    - Letters from politicians, Krome
      Treatment of Haitian refugees.
    - Memos DDJ
    - Misc. Krome and TGK, (2 folders)
    - Model motion
    - Newspaper articles, Krome
    - Notes
    - Official Transcript Proceedings before The Supreme Court of the U.S., Gene McNary V HRC ct A1-89-1332, 1990, Oct. 10
    - Parole, 1991-1992
    - Persecution of Haitian Returnees and Inadequacy of INS Pre-Screening Procedure, 1992
    - Political Asylum Issues, 1989
    - Rape case
    - Rape case, Marie Baptiste
    - Returnees/interviews, for copy, 1992 Feb.-March
    - Simao, Hermes Santos Jr. (Box 11)
    - Stepick - Haitians released from Krome, 1984
    - Stowaways
    - Supplement, Krome, 1998, (6 folders)
    - Supplemental articles and statements, Krome
    - Testimony of Cong. Carrie P. Meek, 1994 June 15
    - Update, Krome, 1996-1997, (3 folders)
    - Update, Krome, 1999
    - Wislaine Theresia's baby case
  - Turner Guilford Knight (TGK) Correctional Center Subseries, undated
    Subseries contains materials related to Turner Guilford Knight (TGK) Correctional Center.
    - Abraham - Prof. (Box 12)
    - Alternative setting for detainees
    - FIAC correspondence
    - TGK forms
    - General information
    - Memos/articles
    - TGK miscellaneous
    - Packet
    - Pro Bono
    - TGK report
    - Support groups/TGK
    - Urgent action/sign-on
  - County Jails Subseries, 1993-2000
    Subseries contains materials related to Florida county jails. The subseries mainly includes affidavits and reports on facility conditions.
    - Complaint letter about the county jail to Representative Ros-Lehtinen (Box 13)
    - County jails visit, 1999 July
    - County jails affidavits, 1996-1997
    - Affidavits, 1998
    - Affidavits continued, 1998
    - Affidavits, 2000
    - Affidavits - Key West, 1998
      Originals.
    - County jail articles
    - County jail's conditions
      Citrus/Hornando/Manatee.
    - Conditions at Varick Street Immigration Detention Center, 1993
    - County Jail - detainees' letters, affidavits, etc., 1998
    - Florida County Jails: INS's Secret Detention World, 1997 Nov.
    - County jails, 1999
    - County jails - Florida
      Pending.
    - Jackson County Jail (Box 14)
    - Jackson County Jail affidavits
    - Jackson county jails inspection reports, FOIA reports, etc., (2 folders)
    - Jackson County Jail notes: detainees
    - Manatee County Jail
    - Oakdale
    - Pike County Jail
    - Private prisons/Kendall
    - Report on county jails, drafts
    - County jail supplement, 1998, (1 of 3)
    - County jail supplement, 1999
  - General Subseries, 1987-2009
    Subseries contains materials related to general detention issues of interest to the FIAC. The subseries mainly includes documents regarding detention procedures and abuses and cases of indefinite detention.
    - Affidavit and client information, expedited removal, 1992-1997 (Box 15)
    - Detention, 1990-1991
    - Detention abuses, 1987-1991, (3 folders)
    - Dying For Decent Care: Bad Medicine in Immigration Custody, 2009 Feb.
    - Indefinite detention, 1997-1999, (2 folders)
    - INS detainees in Florida, 2001
    - INS detainees in Florida, supplement, 2002
    - INS detention, 1989-1990 (Box 16)
    - INS detention, 1996-1997, (2 folders)
    - INS procedures, 1993-1995
    - Post-custody review, undated
- Immigrants and Refugees Series, 1980-2004, (14 boxes)
  Series contains documents related to immigrant and refugee populations of interest to FIAC, particularly Haitian populations. Files primarily deal with issues of deportation and asylum, as well as issues relating to US detention. Files include legal documents such as affidavits and court records and other materials such as newspaper articles, correspondence, government reports, and PR materials. Sensitive and confidential material has been moved to the Legal Files series. Files are arranged in rough alphabetical order.
  - Haitians Subseries, 1981-2004
    Subseries contains documents related primarily to issues of, and cases related to, deportation and asylum specifically within the Haitian community and the Florida Immigrant Advocacy Center's work. Many files deal with the Haitian Boat crises of 2001 and 2002, with some focus on women and children refugees and children stranded in Haiti. Subseries also includes materials on various crises in Haiti, including the AIDs crisis and the 2011 earthquake. Files include articles, letters, asylum seeker statemets, district court pleadings and briefings, documentation on hunger strikes, and court documents regarding interdiction.
    - After the Earthquake, 2011 (Box 17)
    - Air France, 1994
    - AIDS, 1987-1992
    - AIDS comment, 1987-1989
    - Articles, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2001-2002, (2 folders)
    - Articles, Children stranded in Haiti, 1993, (3 folders)
    - Articles, letters to politicians, etc., 1990-1991, (1-3 of 5 folders)
    - Articles, letters to politicians, etc., (4-5 of 5) (Box 18)
    - Asylum seeker statements, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002
    - Attorney General, INS Commissioner, International Affairs, communication, 1994
    - Case #81-1497-CIV-JE, Wilmer Luberisse and Job Dessin, 1981
    - Charter flights, 1994
    - Children - Haiti - reports, 1991-1992, 1995
    - Clinton position paper and article, 1992
    - Coast guard interdiction at sea, 2002
    - Comfort Suites, 2002-2003
    - Conditions in Haiti: Cauler letter, 1997
    - Conference on current migration crisis, Senator Kennedy, 2003 Feb. 5
    - Congressional communication, 1993
    - Congressional hearings,, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002 Oct. 1, (2 folders)
    - Congressional letters, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2001-2002
    - Correspondence with U.S. Department of Justice, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2001-2002
    - Correspondence - Walter Cadman, INS District Director, 1994-1995
    - Different viewpoints, 2002
    - Documentation, U.S. consulate in Haiti, 1996
    - Discriminatory treatment, 2002-2003
    - Detained Haitians, 2003
    - District court briefings II, habeus memos, (2 folders) (Box 19)
    - District court opinions, 1985-1987
    - District court pleadings I, Arellano v. Weinberger, 1984
    - District court pleadings I, 1985-1987, (1-6 of 7 folders)
    - District court pleadings I, 1985-1987, (7 of 7 folders) (Box 20)
    - District court pleadings II, 1986-1989, (2 folders)
    - EAD's, 1993, 1995
    - "Freedom for 24 Haitian women" saga, 2002
    - Funding requests, 1994
    - General - Dow, Mark, Haiti articles, 1994-1996
    - General information, 1994
    - Governor Jeb Bush statement, 2002
    - Haitian asylum, 1992, (7 folders)
    - Haitian asylum seekers, 2002 (Box 21)
    - Haitian asylum seekers, 2003, (3 folders)
    - Congressional letters, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002), 2002-2003
    - FIAC correspondence, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002), 2003
    - EOIR, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002), 2002
    - INS/Human rights organizations response to Haitian boatload, 2002 October 29
    - Legal, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002), 2002-2003
    - Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002 Oct. 29) press coverage, 2002, (5 folders)
    - Smuggling charges, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002), 2003 (Box 22)
    - Summaries/talking points, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001)
    - Talking points; backgrounder; chronology, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002)
    - Urgent actions; resolutions; press releases, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002)
    - Women and children, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2002)
    - Haitian Children Awaiting Visas: A Plea for Help, 1994
      - On file/affidavits, 1993-1997
      - Amnesty International, 1993-1994
      - Amnesty International for children, 1994
      - The Congressional Black Caucus, 1994
      - Congress person, 1993
      - Closing of embassies, undated
      - Letters of support, 1993
      - Mexico, 1994
      - Newspaper articles, 1991-1994
      - Policy, 1993-1994
      - School board of Dade county Florida, 1994
      - Students' work, 1994
    - Haitians in the Dominican Republic, 1996
    - Haiti informational, 1993-1999
    - Haitian issues, 2002-2003
    - Haitian packet attachments, 2002 (Box 23)
    - Haitian packet, 2003, (2 folders)
    - Haitian packet, Haitian boat, 2001 Dec. 3, (4 folders)
    - Haitian Refugees: A People in Search of Hope, 2004 May 1
      - Appendix A: declarations, statements and testimony of detainees and their families and their advocates
      - Appendix B: articles, (1-2 of 5)
    - Haitian Refugees
      - Appendix B: Articles, (3-5 of 5) (Box 24)
      - Appendix C: U.S. policies, declarations, legal decisions, (2 folders)
      - Appendix D: correspondences, press releases, etc., (5 folders)
      - Indices, additional: affidavits and articles
    - Haitian Refugees
      - Missing footnotes documents (Box 25)
    - H.R. 3663: Haitian refugee fairness act, 1994
    - Haitian repatriations, 2000-2001
    - Haiti update, 2000
    - Haitian Women of Miami - Marleine Bastien (forms, memos), 1995
    - Hearing on Haitian detention/interdiction, 1989
    - HIV 1994-1996
    - Informal briefings before U.S. commission on civil rights, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002 June 21
    - Interdiction 1994
    - Interdiction lawsuit, 1984, (3 folders)
    - Media, 1994
    - Miami-Dade commissioner's resolution, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002
    - Miscellaneous, 1992-1994
    - The National Coalition for Haitian Rights (NCHR), 1994, 2003
    - NCHR - expenses, 1994
    - NGO/local organizational support, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002-2003
    - NPR morning edition (Ernest Belisere), 1992 Feb. 11 (Box 26)
    - Oversite hearing on Haitian and Cuban immigrants, 1991
    - Other, 2002
    - Press conference, 2003 March 24
    - Press packet, 2002, November 1
    - Press releases, 1994
    - Press releases, letters to politicians, etc., 2002
    - Press releases, urgent actions, Haitian boat (2001), 2002
    - Processing immigrant visas for Haitians in Mexico, 1988
    - Questions for Haitians returned to Haiti, 2002 Aug.
    - Rally for children, 1993 Sept. 26
    - Randall Robinson hunger strike, 1994
    - Refugee Refoulment: The Forced Return of Haitians under the U.S. - Haitian Interdiction Agreement, 1990 March
    - Reno memo on Toboso, 1994-2002
    - Sign on to American Immigrant Lawyers Association, regarding Illegal Immigration Reform and Immigrant Responsibility Act of 1996 (IIRAIRA), 1997
    - Children stranded in Haiti, sign ons for report faxes, potentials - fax list of names, 1994
    - South Ridge High students, 2002
    - Stepick affidavits master file, 1983-1985
    - St. Thomas University Law School - Parolees, 1993-1994
    - Summaries, 2003
    - Children stranded in Haiti, 1993
    - Supporting documents about Haiti, 2002 August
    - Transcript of hearing, Haitian boat refugee crisis (2001), 2002 Oct. 1
    - U.S. consulate in Haiti, 1993-1994